mr. chairman distinguished members of
the committee thank you for the
invitation
to address you tomorrow is the one-year
anniversary of the day fifty evergreen
students students that I had never met
disrupted my class accusing me of racism
and demanding my resignation I tried to
reason with them I felt no fear because
I knew that whatever my failings might
be bigotry was not among them at that
moment I felt sure I could reach them I
also felt a moral obligation to try that
racism squanders human potential and
erodes human dignity offends me I am
also well-versed in the evolutionary
logic that makes racism durable I should
have had no trouble establishing common
ground their response surprised me it
would take months for me to fully
understand what had happened the
protestors had no apparent interest in
the very dialogue they seemed to invite
I was even more surprised by the
protesters fervor and shouting down my
actual students some of whom had known
me for years the cruelty and derision
reserved for students of color who spoke
in my defense was particularly troubling
if not discussion what did they want I
was one of evergreens most popular
professor's I had evergreens version of
tenure did they really think they could
force my resignation based on a
meritless accusation they did think that
and they were right what I had not
counted on was their alliance with
evergreens new president though the
protestors openly humiliated him the
president of the college partnered with
the mob in private handing them
concession after concession we know this
because the rioters filmed everything
and proudly uploaded it in one
particularly telling video the president
calmly discusses with the leaders of the
protest a demand to target stem faculty
based on the empty assertion that
scientists are particularly prone to
bias in that same video the President
speaks of his plan for those who resist
a new order bring him in train him and
if it doesn't take sanction them he
invites his partners to hold him to it
on the second day of unrest the police
chief called me rioters were stopping
traffic and searching for someone car to
car the chief believed they were
searching for me she was worried for my
safety and helpless to protect me as the
president had ordered her force to stand
down what would have transpired if the
rioters had found me
I still don't know and Isis try I
strongly suspect they don't either the
protests of my class did not emerge out
of the blue in May of 2017 one year
earlier I stood up and spoke in
opposition to a dangerous proposal one
that threatened to establish a racial
hierarchy amongst faculty to those who
have not faced something similar this
likely sounds hyperbolic but one can now
advance such policies and almost
certainly succeed in passing them if
they are properly draped and weaponized
terminology equity for example has taken
on special properties if a person
opposes an equity proposal those
advancing the proposal are secure in
asserting that the person is motivated
by opposition to racial equity itself in
other words they are racist
my opposition to that first equity
proposal was voiced to my colleagues
with no students present demands for my
resignation one year later in May of
2017 were not the result of organic
student confusion they were payback for
violating a de facto code of faculty
conduct in which one's right to speak is
now dictated by adherence to an
ascendant orthodoxy in which one's race
gender and sexual orientation are
paramount the students were on a mission
they were unwitting tools of a witting
movement this committee should take my
tail as cautionary is there a free
speech crisis on college campuses one
can certainly make that argument but
that portrayal is at least as misleading
as it is informative what is occurring
on college campuses is about power and
control
speech is impeded as a last resort used
when people or groups fail to
self-censor in response to a threat of
crippling stigma and the destruction of
their capacity to earn these tools are
being used to unhook the values that
bind us together as a nation equal
protection under the law the presumption
of innocence a free marketplace of ideas
the concept that people should be judged
by the content of their character rather
than the color of their skin yes even
that core tenant of the civil rights
movement is being dismantled
am i alleging a conspiracy no what I
have seen functions much more like a
cult in which the purpose is only
understood by the leaders and the rest
have been seduced into a carefully
architected fiction most of the people
involved in this movement earnestly
believe that they are acting nobly
to end oppression only the leaders
understand that the true goal is to turn
the tables of oppression something is
seriously and dangerously amiss at this
moment in history the center does not
hold partisan polarization and political
corruption have rendered government
ineffective predatory and often cruelly
indifferent to the suffering of American
citizens tribalism is the natural result
evergreens public meltdown placed me in
the eye of the storm and cast me into
the spotlight as a member of the
intellectual dark web I find myself at
the vanguard of an emerging
non-ideological non partisan movement
along with the heterodox Academy and the
foundation for individual rights in
education we are fighting to restore
civility and respect for competing
perspectives the electorate is starved
for honest debate and for the good
governance that follows from it my
advice to this body is to put the nation
and its core values ahead of
partisanship and join us in the center
to end this cultish power grab and
return us to a forward path as a nation
I look forward to your questions what
has been the reaction to what happened
to you both on campus and off campus
have any change has been made the campus
has doubled down on every foolish idea
it was pursuing and has gotten itself
into very serious financial trouble for
lack of students which I should tell you
I warned my colleagues that if they
pursued this false equity proposal that
that would be the result so a rather
predictable disaster is occurring on
campus I do want to push back a little
bit though on the assessment that it is
the left because really it isn't one
left there is an ascendant orthodoxy on
the left that is very troubling
it is quite broad but I think not very
deep then there's a concentrated mirror
image of that on the far right and both
of these things are to be feared the
problem though is when you speak out on
a college campus from a perspective on
the left that does not fit this
orthodoxy you are immediately
categorized as on the right which makes
it look that the left is monolithic and
all shares this opinion that
it's not the case dr. Weinstein what
happened in your classroom which I've
seen videos of was was that was your
classroom that day a safe space for a
free speech zone or neither thank you
for asking me that question
Frese a safe space it looked like it was
safe to me well I believe in something
that could be called a safe space but
what safe space means to me as an
educator is a space safe enough to take
risks which is roughly the opposite
meaning of what is being invoked on
college campuses the answer to your
question is that a free-speech zone
cannot coexist with a safe space because
a safe space by definition according to
this orthodoxy is a place where you are
free from being offended so it cannot it
is mutually exclusive but if you would
allow me to I feel that there's a safe
space could you say this sentence could
you say Donald Trump is President of the
United States could you say that in a
safe space on college campuses today
well it depends which version of safe
space you mean if you mean a safe space
the way it is used in common parlance on
college campuses today then the question
of whether or not you can say it is
contingent on whether or not somebody
will be offended by that observation
think about that
you can't even state a fact a fact
provable all right I saw his tweet this
morning it's provable he's the president
right mr. chairman oh you cannot do that
this shows the absurdity of what is
going on on campuses and you have lived
it in a physical way doctor Stanger has
lived it in a physical way this is what
is scary
dr. Stanger's raising her head at mr.
Weinstein you have the floor so you'd
have to yield time to her but you don't
have to okay I think this is important
enough to warrant a minute or two we are
continuing in this hearing to run up
against the bluntness of the tool that
we have at our disposal for discussing
the issue at hand so there is importance
to what takes place on a college campus
free expression is an a a key feature of
what takes place on college campuses
that make civilization function but the
application of the First Amendment to
that free expression is
almost arbitrary does it matter more
that something takes place at Evergreen
which happens to be public than if it
takes place at Harvard which happens to
be private do those distinctions even
make any sense when fully 80% of the
funding that drives Evergreen is private
tuition money and I don't know what
fraction but a very large fraction of
what drives Harvard is NIH and NSF money
so these distinctions are arbitrary and
what we should be protecting is the
ability to exchange ideas in a way that
actually allows education it is also
true that when people self-censor
because they're afraid of stigma they
may never get around to the place where
somebody blocks their speech and so
there may be no technical violation but
nonetheless the effect is exactly the
same there is also a problem in the
sense that the conflict is really
between members of the audience one
section of the audience is deciding what
other members of the audience can listen
to the person's speech view is inhibited
is almost beside the point it's a
question of whether you can choose what
you want to entertain as a concept and
then when this jumps the fence and
leaves the college campuses and moves
into the outer world we're gonna run
into an even bigger problem where the
tech sector is now the de-facto
governance apparatus for the new public
square and it's private so the First
Amendment doesn't apply take the example
of Harvard which you talked about dr.
Weinstein whether it's DoD funds whether
it's NIH funds or whether it's Pell
grant funding there are so many federal
dollars that underpin the way Harvard
functions and and their budget on an
annual basis and the fact that the
university can penalize students because
they join an outside organization zero
affiliation with Harvard they're not
allowed to be sports captain's they're
not allowed to be considered for
fellowships and I think that is a
significant overstep of the university's
role I wanted to give other panelists an
opportunity to respond dr. Weinstein
well the first thing to say is I'm not a
legal expert but I would certainly
support the idea that leverage generated
by the funding that is given by the
federal government would morally it
would morally be justified to use that
to make sure that college campuses
protect the free expression but I would
also point out that this is not just a
matter
abstract ideas presented by speakers on
campus this is now extending into the
classroom and it's a question of what
one can properly teach in a biology
class for example which may well not be
politically correct but it's nonetheless
necessary for students to understand the
organism that they're studying so
ultimately this is going to manifest in
our competitiveness as a nation if we
decide that there are certain things
that are true in science that can't be
stated in a college classroom then our
students will be under educated relative
to any nation that can solve that
problem so this is really a critical
issue and the use of those funds to to
keep the the campus square open is
entirely valid in my opinion what can we
do so we're not having these ridiculous
PC controversies for the rest of our
lives so we can really try to work out
some good ground rules
yes dr. Weinstein so there's a natural
tension between the duty of a college or
university to curate the content so that
the students are encountering things
that enrich them and it's duty to guard
freedom of expression and and I think we
just could be honest about the fact that
that tension exists I mean peer review
does shut down viewpoints that aren't
deemed of a high quality and that we
don't commonly take that to be an
infringement of free speech as to your
question about the effect of something
like the University of Chicago letter I
must say that there's a paradox here for
those who espouse a libertarian economic
perspective which is the Chicago letter
would seem to protect freedom of
expression better than any other campus
on in the nation that I'm aware of that
presumably will give students who go
there a competitive edge because they
will have been exposed to challenging
ideas and will have sharpened their
toolkit in response and so why is that
letter not spreading why are college
campuses not falling all over themselves
to embrace this in order to collect
those students who are looking for a
college campus that will expose them to
the highest quality material available
so I don't know the answer to that
question but I do find it interesting
that Chicago was able to articulate
these things and survive it and
their colleges have not embraced the
same principles we really don't prepare
most college faculty to be good
instructors in essence and had dawned on
me until I had the good fortune for most
of having it had dawned on me until he
said that there's you sure absolutely
dr. Weinstein would what can you suggest
well let me add something to that he's
are quite right that we don't train
people to teach and we also never spell
out that the the job of an educator is
to teach you how to think not what to
think a fact if somebody at the front of
the room happens to have a perspective
that they hold dear shouldn't mean that
they are attempting to transmit it to
students wholesale they should give them
the tools to evaluate for themselves
unfortunately what we are seeing is the
result of the politicization of of the
Commons effectively and I that that's
the result of two things which is that
people do not feel well represented by
the governance apparatus and of the fact
that they feel a threat of austerity
which is causing them to be tribal so if
you really want to address this problem
people have to understand that they have
more to gain by being patriotic together
than by fighting each other for scraps
and I can't see a way around this the
First Amendment is simply not sufficient
to protect the free exchange of ideas in
the private sector it's not sufficient
to protect it on college campuses that
don't happen to be public and it's
actually not especially useful on public
campuses where it doesn't deal with
issues like censorship our
self-censorship